William Helfand collection of medical ephemera
Medical Historical Library, Harvey Cushing / John Hay Whitney Medical Library
- Loose material in boxes, Series II
  - Box 2: Additional loose ephemera
    - Rupture appliances; Chas. Cluthe and Sons, Bloomfield, N.J., early 20th century (Box 2, Folder 5)
      5 pamphlets, a guarantee certificate to furnish a truss on a 60 day trial, a standard letter in which the recipient's name is typed in, dated 1913; a form for a customer to describe his case; and a return envelope.
    - Rupture appliances: Capt. W. A. Collings, Watertown, N.Y., early 20th century (Box 2, Folder 6)
      5 small pamphlets, a large leaflet, and an envelope addressed in ink to Capt. W.A. Collings, Inc.
    - Rupture appliances: Dr. W. S. Rice, Adams, N.Y., 1890s (Box 2, Folder 7)
      7 items.
    - Rupture appliances: Other companies, early 20th century (Box 2, Folder 8)
      3 items: F. J. Stuart, More Proof that Stuart's Adhesive Plaster-Pads Cure Rupture (St. Louis, Mo., 1907); Surehold Company, Westbrook, Maine, Rupture; and Empire Manufacturing Co., Lockport, N.Y.
    - Advertisements for treatment of asthma, hay-fever, catarrh, and consumption, early 20th century (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Five pamphlets by Frontier Asthma Company, Buffalo, N.Y.; Dr. Blosser, Ltd, London; Dr. F. G. Kinsman, Augusta, Maine; Dr. W. G. Tucker, Mt. Gilead, Ohio (Dr, Nathan Tucker Asthma Specific; and Koch Lung Cure (Koch Inhalations), Philadelphia.
    - Advertisement for Dr. J. D. Albright, "Specialist," Philadelphia, Rectal Diseases, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Title is Rectal Diseases: Their Treatment and Cure Without Operation, "1921 Edition." Contains patient testimonies.
    - Power & Weightman, Philadelphia, Advertisement for Sulphate of Chinchonia, 1855 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Daniel B. Smith, On the Cheaper Alkaloids of the Cinchonas, written at the request of Powers & Weightman. Smith had been President of the Philadelphia College of Pharmacy.
    - Franklin Ford, Jackson, Michigan, remedies for men, ca. 1910 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Two broadsides and a printed letter for remedies for men by Franklin Ford, Jackson, Michigan. These include "Strong Proof that Vitala Cures Men of all Ages."
    - Political pamphlets using medical imagery (Box 2, Folder 13)
      "Curry," "L'Homme au cigare entre les dents," against the Marshall Plan" (1950); and "Cures for What Ails America, Dr. B.M. Goldwater's All Purpose Defoliation Tonic" (1964).
    - Medical and dental humor, 1955 and undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
      3 items: Scartoons / "by a Bona fide Member of the Mystic Order of the Itching Stitch" (Boston: Rust Craft Publishers, 1955); Le Bon Dentiste (Maison M. Brodard, Montpelier); Le Charlatan: Conte humoristique, sold by Louis Conard, Paris.
    - Issue of La Guerre Anti-Tuberculeuse, 1932 April 15 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Popular journal edited by Dr. Victor Simon, Paris. The magazine was the organ of La Ligue Internationale Contre La Tuberculose.
    - William H. Helfand correspondence on the "medicine show", 1981-1985 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      Folder contains information about re-creations of medicine shows, especially correspondence of William Helfand on the Medicine Show exhibition at the American Place Theatre, 1983, for which Helfand lent materials. There is also correspondence on Helfand's talks and publications on the medicine show. This material was formerly inserted loose in Album 11.
    - Additional materials on the "medicine show" (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Additional images and newspaper articles on modern recreations of medicine shows. This material had been inserted loosely in Album 11.
    - Secondary sources on prescription envelopes (Receptkuverter), 1976-2007 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      Includes a letter on prescription envelopes from Hans Otto Loldrup, Dansk Farmaceutforening, to Helfand, October 30, 1979. See Albums 12-15.
    - Sergio Rocchietta, typescript, "Physicians and Apothecaries in Moliere, in Music," no date. (Box 2, Folder 19)
      Found loose in one of the albums.